Guide to the Courtland Cox papers, 1963-2021 RL.11350
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Pan-African Congress, 1967-1978; undated; 2
  - Randall Robinson to Joshua Guberman, Boston Broadcasters, 1974 Aug. 27 (Box 2)
  - Winston Wiltshire to Cox, 1972 May 30 (Box 2)
  - Cox to Cox, 1973 Jan. 25 (Box 2)
  - "To African People Worldwide", undated (Box 2)
  - "The Liberation Struggle in Namibia: Its Problems and Advances", 1974 June 19-27 (Box 2)
    By Sam Nujoma
  - Regional mailing list for Canada and United States, undated (Box 2)
  - Embassy of Jamaica to Temporary Secretariat of the Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1973 Sept. 25 (Box 2)
  - Pan-African Economic and Political Review Outline, undated (Box 2)
  - Cox Itinerary, undated (Box 2)
  - Sixth Pan-African Congress folder, 1974 June 19-27 (Box 2)
  - "A Selection of Documents," Sixth-Pan African Congress, 1974 June 19-27 (Box 2)
    Contains mostly finanical papers
  - Cox to Mr. and Mrs. Samuel Coleman, undated (Box 2)
  - Untitled notes, undated (Box 2)
  - B.M. Cloud to Brother Ahh Golayemi, 1974 July 27 (Box 2)
  - Guinea Embassy in Tanzania to Provisional Secretariat to Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 Aug. 14 (Box 2)
  - H.H. Mweetwa to Secretary-General of the Pan-African Congress, 1974 Aug. 23 (Box 2)
  - Smart A. Ekpo to Secretariat of the Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 Aug. 17 (Box 2)
  - O.O. Ogunidpe to Cox, 1974 Aug. 14 (Box 2)
  - Callie White to Geri M. Stark, 1974 March 14 (Box 2)
  - Eusi Kwayana to C.L.R. James, 1974 Sept. 3 (Box 2)
  - Jean O'Barr to Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1984 July 11 (Box 2)
  - Personal greeting card to Dar Es Salaam, Tanzania, 1974 July 26 (Box 2)
  - Imamu Amiri Baraka to Cox, 1974 Aug. 2 (Box 2)
  - Daniel Britz to Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 Aug. 7 (Box 2)
  - A.S. Tembo to Secretary-General of the Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 July 3 (Box 2)
  - Hailou Wolde-Giorghis to Scretary-General of the Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 Aug. 6 (Box 2)
  - Cox to Bob Brown, draft letter, undated (Box 2)
  - Black Students and the Impossible Revolution, undated (Box 2)
    Vincent Harding, Institute of the Black World
  - Transafrica Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1978 June 28 (Box 2)
  - After the Arusha Declaration, 1967 Oct. 16 (Box 2)
    Julius K. Nyerere
  - The Arusha Declaration, 1967 (Box 2)
    Julius K. Nyerere, President of the United Republic of Tanzania
  - Tanganyika African National Union guidelines, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Working Paper: An Overview of Third World Culture and Political Struggle, undated (Box 2)
    James Garrett
  - National Council of Churches Proposed Amendments to NCC Constitution and By-laws, 1973 Sept. 5 (Box 2)
  - ASCRIA (foreign) flyer, "Is your country also playing these games with imperialism?", 1975 Aug. 25 (Box 2)
  - Response to a toast by President Kenneth D. Kaunda of Zambia at a White House dinner given in his honor by President Gerald Ford, 1975 Apr. 5 (Box 2)
    Reports, minutes, background materials, itineraries, and other materials related Cox's role as Secretary General at the Pan-African Congress in Tanzania, held in 1974.
  - Carol Louise, Assistant Secretary for Public Affairs, to Cox regarding South Africa and the United Nations, 1974 Nov. 29 (Box 2)
  - Dick Clark (U.S. Senate) to P.M. Johannes Vorster regarding Terrorism Act, 1975 Sept. 22 (Box 2)
  - "FATH" Poster, Palestine National Liberation Movement, undated (Box 2)
  - List of film strips available at the Afro-American Studies Resource Center, undated (Box 2)
  - Flyer, Arusha Konakri Institute open house, 1973 Dec. 28 (Box 2)
  - Book jacket, The Destruction of Black Civilization, undated (Box 2)
    Chancellor Williams
  - Proposal, African Friendship House, undated (Box 2)
  - "Africa Insight," Magazine planning documents for first issue, 1976 Apr. (Box 2)
  - Gisler Mapunda resume, 1974 Aug. 5 (Box 2)
  - Cox to Shirley Graham DuBois, typescript, undated (Box 2)
  - Intelligence report, vol. 1, no. 1, Center for National Security Studies, 1975 (Box 2)
  - WAREJEAJI meeting minutes, 1974 July 30 (Box 2)
  - Press relesae, World Council of Churches regarding Repression in South Africa and Namibia, undated (Box 2)
  - Ratoon Bulletin, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Liberation Rally flyer, 1973 May 22 (Box 2)
  - "Marcus Garvey" pamphlet pubished by the Information Department National Joint Action Committee, undated (Box 2)
  - First draft, Sixth Pan-African Congress, undated (Box 2)
  - Owasu Sadaukai to Cox, 1973 Oct. 16-18 (Box 2)
  - Tentative agenda for Nov. 3-4 Meeting, Sixth Pan-African Congress, undated (Box 2)
  - Speech draft, Amiri Baraka, 1974 Sept. (Box 2)
  - Memorandum, Loretta Hobbs Taylor to Cox, 1974 Oct. 7 (Box 2)
  - Assorted notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Letter in French, undated (Box 2)
    Warwick, Bermuda
  - Letters from Eusi Kwayana regarding the Caribbean delegation, Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 May 13-18 (Box 2)
  - Letter to Cox, 1972 March 4 (Box 2)
  - Cox to Geisler Mapunda, 1974 Aug. 13 (Box 2)
  - Dar Es Salaam Steering Committee for Sixth Pan-African Congress meeting minutes, 1974 April 30 (Box 2)
  - Keorapetse Kgositsile to Cox, 1972 Sept. 8 (Box 2)
  - African Liberation Day notes, undated (Box 2)
  - Interview with Ahmed Adou, ambassador, undated (Box 2)
  - 1972 Pan-African Congress Structural and Programatic Clarifications, 1971 Dec. 15 (Box 2)
  - Secretary General, Sixth Pan-African Congress, to Dr. Philip Potter, 1974 July 29 (Box 2)
  - United Front Against Imperialists letter of concern to Steering Committee of the Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1973 Feb. 9 (Box 2)
  - Sixth Pan-African Congress outline, undated (Box 2)
  - Sixth Pan-African Congress planning document, undated (Box 2)
  - Internal memo with planning suggestions, undated (Box 2)
  - Assorted memorandums for planning, undated (Box 2)
  - Visiting delegation agenda, undated (Box 2)
  - Seventh Pan-African Congress Proposal Structure, undated (Box 2)
  - Sixth Pan-African Congress information flyer, undated (Box 2)
  - Sixth Pan-African Congress operation budget, undated (Box 2)
  - An Appeal for Financial Support, Sixth Pan-African Congress, undated (Box 2)
  - Proposed Conference Structure, Sixth Pan-African Congress, undated (Box 2)
  - Midwest District Meeting of State Coordinators meeting minutes (Chicago, IL), 1973 Sept. 8 (Box 2)
  - History of Southern Africa, undated (Box 2)
  - Draft call for the Sixth Pan-African Congress, undated (Box 2)
  - Winston Wiltshire to John Malacela, 1972 July 15 (Box 2)
  - Ben Mkara to Winston Wiltshire, 1972 July 12 (Box 2)
  - Draft for Proposal of Science Technology and Development, undated (Box 2)
  - Assorted country statistics, undated (Box 2)
  - State of Minnesota District to Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1973 Sept. 24 (Box 2)
  - Investment in Jamaica, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Form letter for supprt of Sixth Pan-African Congress drafted by Cox, undated (Box 2)
  - The Rational Choice, 1973 Jan. 25 (Box 2)
    By Julius K. Nyerere
  - Press release, United Nations Security Council, 1976 June 19 (Box 2)
  - Candid photographs from Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 (Box 2)
    Six color photographs from Tanzania taken during the Sixth Pan-African Congress. Includes shots of Courtland Cox and Roosevelt Brown.
  - Letter from Frankie Cox to U.S. Customs agent, 1973 (Box 2)
    Letter from Frankie Cox, wife of Courtland Cox, to a U.S. Customs agent regarding a broken bottle of haircare product.
  - Photographs, Sixth Pan-African Congress, 1974 June 19-27 (Box 2)
  - Pan-African Congress, Tanzania, 1972-1974; 6 folders (Box 7)
    Contains a rich assemblage of meeting minutes, planning notes; conference agendas; lists of participants; calls for action; platforms on issues such as apartheid, French colonialism, and black power; reports during and after the Congress; photocopied clippings; and articles by Cox on the conference.
- Subject Files, 1963-1987; undated; 3
  - AFCO Form letter, 1973 Jan. 31 (Box 3)
  - African Liberation Day Coordinating Committee, 1972 May 27 (Box 3)
    Program, handouts, press release
  - African Liberation Support Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 3)
    Handouts, correspondence, position papers
  - African Policy and Black Americans, "Can the Blacks do for Africa what the Jews did for Israel?", undated (Box 3)
    By Martin Weil
  - Afrika Must Unite, undated (Box 3)
    Flyers, newsletters
  - Angola Crisis, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    Form letter, position papers
  - As Sorry as Guilty Dirt: The Abiding Shame of Reagan's Romance with BAASKAP, undated (Box 3)
    by Michael Thelwell
  - Assorted protest documents, 1973; undated (Box 3)
    Gulf Boycott, ALSC Campaign to Repeal Byrd Amendment, Pan-African Liberation Committee
  - Assorted booklets and brochures, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Assorted periodicals, 1963-1977; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Assorted reports, undated (Box 3)
  - Black Academy of Arts and Letters Awards Banquet, 1971 Sept. 19 (Box 3)
    Program, newspaper
  - Black Executives in Denominational Structures, 1973 (Box 3)
    Reports, meeting agends, form letter, questionnaire
  - Castle Gordon Pilot Project, ca. 1972 (Box 3)
    Jamaica
  - Center for Black Education, 1968-1972; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Brochures, newsletters, curriculum, article drafts, outlines, meeting agendas
  - Analytical Report on Southern Africa Compiled by Center for Black Education and African Liberation Day Committee, 1972 (Box 3)
  - China Diplomacy photographs, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    Two photographs featuring Courtland Cox during his association with Marion Barry. One photograph was taken in China and the other in Washington, DC.
  - "CIA Agent Baraka Expose", undated (Box 3)
  - Committee for a Free South Africa, undated (Box 3)
    Flyers
  - Dar Es Salaam Liberation Support Group, African Liberation Day Dance Handout, undated (Box 3)
  - "The Development of a Political Consciousness: An Autobiography", undated (Box 3)
    By Ejaffa
  - FBI Memorandums on Cox, 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - FBI Surveillance reports on Cox, 1970 (Box 3)
  - FBI Memorandums and files on Cox, 1969-1974 (Box 3)
    Includes some photographs
  - FBI Memorandums on assorted individuals and groups related to Cox, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Ralph Featherstone, 1970 March 11 (Box 3)
    Newspaper, obituary
  - Fifth Annual Conference of Black Students in Medicine and Science Schedule, 1973 Dec. 26-30 (Box 3)
  - FOIA requests, FBI files, 1969-1972 (Box 7)
  - Furrows by Charles Cobb (photocopy), undated (Box 3)
  - Imamu Amiri Baraka to Habari Gani, Congress of African People, 1973 Sept. 2 (Box 3)
  - International Peace Research Association information packet, undated (Box 3)
  - Interrelationships between economic and demographic chabge in Africa and Latin America, draft, undated (Box 3)
  - George Jackson, 1971 Aug. 21 (Box 3)
    Funeral program
  - The Makonde Tradition, undated (Box 3)
    Information packet
  - March on Washington photograph, 1964 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Enlarged photograph mounted on posterboard of meeting between Courtland Cox, A. Phillip Randolph, Martin Luther King Jr., Roy Wilkins, Bayard Rustin, James Farmer, Whitney Young, and Jack Greenberg. Includes names of individuals.
  - Minority Business Development Agency, 1995-2000 (Box 4)
    Two research reports, one on The Emerging Minority Marketplace and the other on The Minority Business Challenge.
  - Minority Business Development Agency, 1995-2000 (Box 5)
    Four photographs enlarged and mounted on foamcore boards. Captions are as follows: 1) "Secretary of Commerce Bill Daley is congratulating an awardee at the annual MBDA Business Conference, either 1998 or 1999" 2) "My Senior staffa at MBDA. Picture taken in either 1999 or 2000." 3) "Talk to Vernon Jordan at Ron Brown's Memorial Service. April 1996." 4) "Ron Brown chairing a Diversity Council Meeting at the Department of Commerce. I am sitting next to him with glasses. I was at the tme the Director of the Office of Civil Rights at the Dept, 1995."
  - National Black Assembly, 1972 (Box 3)
    Gary, IN; agenda, position papers
  - National Council of Churches Commission on Justice and Liberation, Consultation or Development, undated (Box 3)
    Conference binder
  - Newspaper clippings photocopies, 1973-1988 (Box 3)
  - Report on the Trip to the Organization of African Unity, 10th Anniversary Celebration and General Session, 1973 May 17-31 (Box 3)
  - Pan-African Early Education Center newsletter, 1974 Jan. (Box 3)
  - Petition to the Attorney General of North Carolina (Rufus Edmisten), undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs, China Trip and Gallows Island, 1984; undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Photograph of Courtland Cox and Rudy Lombard, undated (Box 3)
    Black and white photograph of Courtland Cox and Rudy Lombard, veterans of SNCC and CORE, respectively.
  - Second World Black and African Festival of Art and Culture meeting minutes, 1973 Nov. 12 (Box 3)
  - Second World Black and African Festival of Art and Culture Appendix A, 1975 Jan. 4 to Feb. 1 (Box 3)
  - Second World Black and African Festival of Art and Culture, Third meeting, International Committee, 1973 Nov. 8-13 (Box 3)
    Meeting reports, Documents 035-046, no. 039 missing
  - Colloquium on Black Civilization and Education, Third meeting, International Committee, Second World Black and African Festival of Art and Culture, 1975 Jan. (Box 3)
  - District of Columbia/Maryland members, Upper South Region, Second World Black and African Festival of Art and Culture, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Tanzania, assorted reports, undated (Box 3)
  - Technology and Techniques of the Black African Societies, Presented to the Committee for the Second World Festival of Negro Arts and Culture, 1973 Oct. 29 (Box 3)
  - Kwame Ture (Stokely Carmichael) photographs, 1998 (Box 3)
    Two photographs of Stokely Carmichael, one featuring a group shot with Louis Farrakahan, Chuck McDew, John Lewis, Phil Hutchings, and Marion Barry.
  - Second World Black and African Festival of Arts and Culture Background Information, undated (Box 3)
  - Science and Technology meeting minutes, Howard University, School of Engineering, 1973 July 11 (Box 3)
  - SNCC 50th Anniversary Conference, 2009-2010 (Box 4)
    Conference Program, Planning Committee Minutes, and Photobook from SNCC 50th Anniversary Conference. Held in Raleigh, North Carolina April 15-18, 2010.
  - Untitled notebooks, undated (Box 3)
  - Unemployment and Poverty Action Council press release, James Forman, 1987 Dec. 19 (Box 3)
  - Westerfield Conference on Economic Development, conference packet, 1973 Oct. 25-27 (Box 3)
  - Pan-African Cultural Festival in Algiers photographs, 1969 (Box 3)
    Eight candid color photographs from the 1969 Pan-African Cultural Festival held in Algiers, Algeria. Includes photographs of Eldridge Cleaver, Don Lee, Sterling Brown, and Ted Joans.
  - Revolutionary Action Party executive mandate number 117: Techniques for the organization of the Black Resistance Movement, 1960s? (Box 3)
    Thermofax copy of a 6-page memorandum with instructions for recruiting and communicating across the movement, including discussions of ideal recruits, warnings of police infiltration and wire-tapping, and other recommendations for protecting oneself and one's network
  - Photo album of Courtland Cox and US Postal Stamp honoring the March on Washington, 2003? (Box 6)
  - Printed material and correspondence, 1963-1974 (Box 7)
  - Writings by Courtland Cox, 1970s (Box 7)
    Contains various writings: partial interview script, with "Mimi," Cox, and Charlie Cobb, on black liberation and other topics; various writings on black power, apartheid, and minority economic justice; and a bibliography on works about insurgencies, guerilla warfare, and non-conventional war.
- Audiovisual Materials, 1968-1971 and undated
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiocassettes are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of listening copies.
  - Bobby Seale, 1968 May 20 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL-11350-CS-0001)
  - On contradiction, Jim Forman, 1970 February 1 (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL-11350-CS-0002)
  - The split in the BPP [Black Panther Party?], 1971 March (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL-11350-CS-0003)
  - Rap Brown / Del Walters / Bill Kunsher, 1969 April (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL-11350-CS-0004)
  - Bobby Seals [Bobby Seale] / Ernest White Show, undated (Box 6, Audio-cassette RL-11350-CS-0005)
- Electronic Records, 2009-2021
  Series contains electronic records that must be requested and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions.
  - Minority Business Development Agency, 2009-2020; Approximately 30 files; 30 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11350-SET-0001)
    Includes document files in PDF, MS Word, and MS Excel formats.
  - CoxPublic miscellaneous documents, 2011-2021; Approximately 30 files; 25 megabytes. (Digital-materials RL11350-SET-0001)
    Includes document files in MS Word, PDF, MS PowerPoint, and OpenDocument Text formats.